<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Botmaster Documentation</title>
    <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Botmaster Documentation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>MIT</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 17:08:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Other Articles</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/other-articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 17:08:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/other-articles/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;other-articles&#34;&gt;OTHER ARTICLES&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;botmaster-or-botkit-botmaster-or-botkit&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;botmaster-or-botkit&#34;&gt;Botmaster or botkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials (coming soon)</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 20:42:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/tutorials/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;coming-soon&#34;&gt;Coming soon&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with Botmaster</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 01:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;working-with-botmaster&#34;&gt;Working with Botmaster&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CHANGELOG</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/changelog/CHANGELOG/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 19:55:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/changelog/CHANGELOG/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;patch-2-2-2&#34;&gt;PATCH: 2.2.2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This patch allows users to set the userId from a sender when using the bot socket.io class. socket now needs to be opened with something like this on the client side:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;var socket = io(&#39;?botmasterUserId=wantedUserId&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See updated Botmaster Socket.io bot mini-tutorial &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/socketio-setup/#botmaster-socket-io-bot-mini-tutorial&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;minor-botmaster-2-2-0&#34;&gt;MINOR: Botmaster 2.2.0&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This minor release allows developers to create news instances of Botmaster without bots settings by writing something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
const MessengerBot = Botmaster.botTypes.MessengerBot;
.
.
const botmaster = new Botmaster();
.
. // full settings objects omitted for brevity
.
const messengerBot = new MessengerBot(messengerSettings);
const slackBot = new SlackBot(slackSettings);
const twitterBot = new TwitterBot(twitterSettings);
const socketioBot = new SocketioBot(socketioSettings);
const telegramBot = new TelegramBot(telegramSettings);

botmaster.addBot(messengerBot);
botmaster.addBot(slackBot);
botmaster.addBot(twitterBot);
botmaster.addBot(socketioBot);
botmaster.addBot(telegramBot);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because it might be viewed as cleaner by some to add bots in the following way rather than doing this in the constructor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;patch-botmaster-2-1-1&#34;&gt;PATCH: Botmaster 2.1.1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This patch fixes a bug whereby one couldn&amp;rsquo;t instantiate a botmaster object that would use socket.io in all reasonably expected ways. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jdwuarin/botmaster/pull/2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;minor-botmaster-2-1-0&#34;&gt;MINOR: Botmaster 2.1.0&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This version adds support for socket.io bots within the botmaster core. This is the last
bot class that will be in the core&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;major-botmaster-2-0-0&#34;&gt;MAJOR: Botmaster 2.0.0&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new version, a lot of new things were added to Botmaster. A few others were removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;breaking-changes&#34;&gt;Breaking Changes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were using SessionStore in version 1.x.x, you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to anymore in version 2.x.x. They have been scratched for the far more common middleware design pattern common in so many other frameworks (e.g. express). Middleware can be hooked into right before receiving an update and right before sending out a message. It fits ideally with people wanting to setup session storage at these points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;adding-slack&#34;&gt;Adding Slack&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support for Slack as the fourth channel supported by Botmaster has been added. Using the Events API, you can now send and receive messages on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;get-user-info&#34;&gt;get User info&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the platform supports it and the bot class you are using supports it too, you can now use the &lt;code&gt;bot.getUserInfo&lt;/code&gt; method to retrieve basic information on a user, including their name and profile pic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;bug fixes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any release, a bunch of bugfixes were done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Botmaster v 2.2.2</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 19:25:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/home/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-botmaster&#34;&gt;What is botmaster?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botmaster is a lightweight highly extendable, highly configurable chatbot framework. It was meant to be used both in small scale and large scale projects. Its purpose is to integrate your chatbot into a variety of messaging channels - currently Facebook Messenger, Slack, Twitter DM, Telegram and socket.io. Using botmaster looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
const config = require(./config);
const botsSettings = [{ telegram: config.telegramSettings },
                      { messenger: config.messengerSettings },
                      { twitter: config.twitterSettings },
                      { slack: config.slackSettings }];

const botmasterSettings = { botsSettings };

const botmaster = new Botmaster(botmasterSettings);

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;Right back at you!&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;botmaster-is-platform-agnostic&#34;&gt;Botmaster is platform agnostic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botmaster is platform agnostic in two important ways. Firstly, out of the box, developers can have bots running on Facebook Messenger, Slack, Twitter DM, Telegram and their personal webapp/app via socket.io with not only a standardized text message format, but also a standardized attachment format. Secondly, BotMaster makes no assumptions about the back-end bot itself - you can write code that allows BotMaster to call conversational engines such as IBM Watson&amp;rsquo;s conversation API, open source frameworks or even write the conversation engine yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;botmaster-s-philosophy&#34;&gt;Botmaster&amp;rsquo;s Philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its philosophy is to minimise the amount of code developers have to write in order to create 1-on-1 conversational chatbots that work on multiple platforms. It does so by defining a standard with respect to what format messages take and how 1-on-1 conversations occur. Messages to/from the various messaging channels supported are all mapped onto this botmaster standard, meaning the code you write is much reduced when compared to a set of point:point integrations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 17:09:45 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-started&#34;&gt;GETTING STARTED&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;installation-installation&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;quickstart-quickstart&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;quickstart&#34;&gt;Quickstart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-set-up-getting-set-up&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;getting-set-up&#34;&gt;Getting set up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;facebook-messenger-setup-messenger-setup&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;messenger-setup&#34;&gt;Facebook Messenger Setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slack-setup-slack-setup&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;slack-setup&#34;&gt;Slack Setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;socket-io-setup-socketio-setup&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;socketio-setup&#34;&gt;Socket.io Setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;twitter-setup-twitter-setup&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;twitter-setup&#34;&gt;Twitter Setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;telegram-setup-telegram-setup&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;telegram-setup&#34;&gt;Telegram setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;webhooks-webhooks&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;webhooks&#34;&gt;Webhooks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Botmaster or Botkit?</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/other-articles/botmaster-or-botkit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 17:07:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/other-articles/botmaster-or-botkit/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use Botmaster If you want to build platform agnostic conversational bots using a system like Watson Conversation [or your own system] to manage 1 on 1 conversations (On Messenger, Slack, Twitter, Telegram, socket.io or more). e.g. a personal assistant, customer support etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use Botkit if you want to build platform dependant bots on either Slack or Twilio while managing simple conversations based on regex or also more complex ones using again Watson Conversation or wit etc. You can now also use Microsoft Bot Framework with Botkit. Although I&amp;rsquo;m not too sure why one would want to use  wouldn&amp;rsquo;t just use MS Bot Framework without Botkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;main-article&#34;&gt;Main article&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it might seem at first glance like the two frameworks (and other similar ones out there) were created with the same goal in mind, things are quite far from that. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at how one of these frameworks compare, namely Botkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botkit was initially created to allow developers to easily build bots of all types that would be available on Slack. Although it now allows developers to build bots for twilio IP messaging and Facebook Messenger too. It was first published in December 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botmaster, on the other hand, is a lightweight framework created after answering the following question: How can I minimise the amount of code a developer has to write in order to create a 1-on-1 conversational chatbot that works on multiple different platforms. It was first published to Github on August 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the differences in application intents between both frameworks, the design differs in many ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;message-format&#34;&gt;Message format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botkit&amp;rsquo;s messages are only standardized to some extent. Because Botkit it not opinionated, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any assumption on what a message attachments or message quick_replies should look like and what they would map to on different platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that a Facebook messenger message with an image attachments will look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;{
  user: &amp;lt;id_of_sender&amp;gt;,
  channel: &amp;lt;id_of_sender&amp;gt;, // also
  timestamp: &amp;lt;unix miliseconds timestamp&amp;gt;,
  seq: &amp;lt;message_sequence_id&amp;gt;,
  mid: &amp;lt;message_id&amp;gt;,
  attachments: [
    {
      type: &#39;image&#39;,
      payload: {
        url: &#39;https://scontent.xx.fbcdn.net/v/.....&#39;
      }
    }
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a Twilio IPM message (Twilio IPM only supports text) will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;{ ChannelSid: &amp;lt;some_id&amp;gt;,
  EventType: &#39;onMessageSent&#39;,
  InstanceSid: &amp;lt;some_id&amp;gt;,
  Attributes: &#39;{}&#39;,
  DateCreated: &#39;2016-07-29T18:42:35.686Z&#39;,
  Index: &#39;1&#39;,
  From: &#39;SneakyQuincyEssex&#39;,
  MessageSid: &amp;lt;some_id&amp;gt;,
  Identity: &#39;SneakyQuincyEssex&#39;,
  Body: &#39;yo&#39;,
  AccountSid: &amp;lt;some_id&amp;gt;,
  text: &#39;yo&#39;,
  from: &#39;SneakyQuincyEssex&#39;,
  to: undefined,
  user: &#39;SneakyQuincyEssex&#39;,
  channel: &amp;lt;some_id&amp;gt; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the nature of Twilio and the nature of channels and how they are dealt with, this makes sense. We&amp;rsquo;ll look at what other differences this brings in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standardization is at the heart of Botmaster. The framework was really created for that purpose. In order to do that, the Facebook Messenger message format was chosen and adopted. This means that when your botmaster object receives an &amp;lsquo;update&amp;rsquo; event from anywhere (twitter, telegram as of this writing), you can be sure that it will be of the same format as a similar message that would come from Messenger.
Typically, it would look something like this for a message with an image attachment. Independant of what platform the message comes from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;{
  raw: &amp;lt;platform_specific_raw_update&amp;gt;,
  sender: {
    id: &amp;lt;id_of_sender&amp;gt;
  },
  recipient: {
    id: &amp;lt;id_of_the_recipent&amp;gt; // will typically be the bot&#39;s id
  },
  timestamp: &amp;lt;unix_miliseconds_timestamp&amp;gt;,
  message: {
    mid: &amp;lt;message_id&amp;gt;,
    seq: &amp;lt;message_sequence_id&amp;gt;,
    attachments: [
      {
        type: &#39;image&#39;,
        payload: {
          url: &#39;https://scontent.xx.fbcdn.net/v/.....&#39;
        }
      }
    ]
  }
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows developers to handle these messages in on place only rather than doing it in multiple ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bot-object&#34;&gt;The bot object&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confusion may [and most likely will] arise when trying to understand how the bot objects returned with each message differ between both frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botkit has a concept of a controller. Controllers are not platform agnostic according to their definition. So for example a Twilio IPM controller will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;var controller = Botkit.twilioipmbot({
    debug: false,
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This controller could then spawn new Twilio IMP bots. Bots all have a fixed endpoint with a port that can be defined if you need multiple bots of the same type. The bot object is returned with every event and you can then do things like send a message or reply etc with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For messenger, it would look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const controller = Botkit.facebookbot({
  access_token: messengerCredentials.pageToken,
  verify_token: messengerCredentials.verifyToken,
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOTE: Because of the fixed endpoint and the fact that Botkit does not (according to their code as of Aug 18th 2016) verify the integrity of the requests using the Facebook App Secret, I would advise against using it as this means that anyone can make a request to &lt;a href=&#34;https://YOUR_SERVER_URL:PORT_CHOSEN/facebook/receive&#34;&gt;https://YOUR_SERVER_URL:PORT_CHOSEN/facebook/receive&lt;/a&gt; and fake requests from Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can have multiple controllers in your app. But you will have to manage the various types of incoming messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botmaster does not have this concept of a controller. In fact, if you are coming from Botkit, you can think of Botmaster as a sort of supercontroller from which you can create a bot of any type as in this example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;
// just an example to show what types of settings are expected
const otherMessengerSettings = {
  credentials: {
    verifyToken: messengerCredentials.verifyToken,
    pageToken: messengerCredentials.pageToken, // access_token in Botkit
    fbAppSecret: messengerCredentials.fbAppSecret,
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook_some_random_string&#39;,
}

const botsSettings = [{ telegram: telegramSettings }, // settings found elsewhere
                      { messenger: messengerSettings }, // settings found elsewhere
                      { messenger: otherMessengerSettings },
                      { twitter: twitterSettings},]; // settings found elsewhere

const botmaster = new Botmaster({settings: botsSettings});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bot objects are created under the hood and events received by each of them will be relayed to the Botmaster in the standardized Messenger format mentioned in the Message format part. Events are called updates and receiving them looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the bot object would have been created with any of the 4 settings mentioned. Note the fact that there are 2 messenger settings. Because Botmaster requires an endpoint to be specified in the settings, nothing more than specifying it has to be done there. We recommend people to include some sort of a key in their endpoint as added security for Messenger (on top of the integrity verification from the Facebook app secret) and as basic security for Telegram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;working-with-webhooks&#34;&gt;Working with webhooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to receive messages, some platforms make the use of webhooks. Which means they will send requests to some endpoints on your server. In order to do that, both frameworks make the use of express() app objects under the hood. Botkit does so for Messenger, Twilio IPM and some of the Slack solutions. Botmaster does do for Messenger and Telegram (for now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard way to deal with this in Botkit is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const port = 3000;

controller.setupWebserver(port, function(err, webserver) {
  controller.createWebhookEndpoints(webserver)
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, this will create an express() webserver and send it onto the &lt;code&gt;createWebhookEndpoints&lt;/code&gt; function. The server will now listen onto the &lt;code&gt;facebook/receive&lt;/code&gt; endpoint on port 3000 if it is a Messenger controller. It will listen onto the &lt;code&gt;&#39;/twilio/receive&#39;&lt;/code&gt; for Twilio IPM and &lt;code&gt;&#39;/slack/receive&#39;&lt;/code&gt; for Slack (if using one of the services that uses webhooks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you might want to use your own express() app webserver to use accross multiple controllers or to serve all sorts of other purposes. You would do this like that in Botkit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const express = require(&#39;express&#39;);
const app = express();
const bodyParser = require(&#39;body-parser&#39;);

app.use(bodyParser.json());
app.use(bodyParser.urlencoded({ extended: true }));
.
.
.
controller.createWebhookEndpoints(app, bot, () =&amp;gt; {
    console.log(&#39;This bot is online!!!&#39;);
});

app.listen(3000, function() {
  console.log(&#39;Server up&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Botmaster, instantiating a botmaster object, will by default just start an express server under the hood for you and make it listen onto port 3000. If you want it to listen onto another port, you can just do something like this when instantiating botmaster:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const port = 3001;
const botmaster = new Botmaster({ settings: botsSettings,
                                 port: port });
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The webhook endpoints will be set according to your settings. Go to &lt;a href=&#34;Readme.md#webhooks&#34;&gt;webhooks&lt;/a&gt; in the main readme to read some more about webhooks in Botmaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to use your own express app, you would do as follows in Botmaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const express = require(&#39;express&#39;);
const app = express();
const bodyParser = require(&#39;body-parser&#39;);

app.use(bodyParser.json());
app.use(bodyParser.urlencoded({ extended: true }));
.
.
.
const botmaster = new Botmaster({settings: botsSettings,
                                 app: app});

app.listen(3000, function() {
  console.log(&#39;Server up&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, Botkit will use different express app webservers for each controller. Botmaster, as mentioned earlier, is a sort of supercontroller. Because of that, it uses the same express webserver accross all channels by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;supported-platforms&#34;&gt;Supported Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are platforms that are supported out of the box. Both frameworks allow developers to write their own integrations and npm packages might exist for the a platform you are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Botmaster&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Botkit&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Facebook Messenger&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Slack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Twilio IPM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Twitter DM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Telegram&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WebSockets&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;MS Bot framework&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conversations&#34;&gt;Conversations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botkit allows developers to specify a deterministic conversation flow within the code to simplify such flows. This is definitely handy and something that can help when creating Slack and Twilio bots&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Botmaster was initialy built mainly as a standardization agnostic layer that assumes your messages will be sent to some sort of AI service like Watson Conversation and others, this hasn&amp;rsquo;t been builtin to the first version. This is however something that will come soon (in a different form from the ones in Botkit). Depending on requests however, it could come sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this all made some sort of sense to you and that you are now able to make a sensible decision with respect to which framework to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realize there are other frameworks out there too that I haven&amp;rsquo;t mentioned. If anyone would like to look into them and tell me what the differences are, I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to add them to another file.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Botmaster Basics</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/botmaster-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 01:31:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/botmaster-basics/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, by now you&amp;rsquo;ve gathered your credentials for at least one platform and got some basic bot running. We remember from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/quickstart&#34;&gt;quickstart&lt;/a&gt; and the various Setup guides in &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started&#34;&gt;getting-started&lt;/a&gt; that we can start our botmaster server like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
.
. // full settings object omitted for brevity
.
const botsSettings = [{ telegram: telegramSettings },
                      { messenger: messengerSettings },
                      { twitter: twitterSettings },
                      { slack: slackSettings },
                      { socketio: socketioSettings }];

const botmasterSettings = {
  botsSettings: botsSettings,
  // by default botmaster will start an express server that listens on port 3000
  // you can pass in a port argument here to change this default setting:
  port: 3001
}

const botmaster = new Botmaster(botmasterSettings);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;settings&#34;&gt;Settings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;botmasterSettings&lt;/code&gt; object has the following parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Parameter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;botsSettings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;An &lt;code&gt;array&lt;/code&gt; of platform specific settings. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/quickstart&#34;&gt;Quickstart&lt;/a&gt; to see an example of those and the various setup guides in &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting started&lt;/a&gt; to see how to get started with the various platforms.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;port&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;optional&lt;/strong&gt;) The port to use for your webhooks (see &lt;a href=&#34;#webhooks&#34;&gt;webhooks&lt;/a&gt; to understand more about webhooks). This will only be used if the &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; parameter is not provided. Otherwise, it will be ignored&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;app&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;optional&lt;/strong&gt;) An &lt;code&gt;express.js&lt;/code&gt; app object to mount the &lt;code&gt;webhookEnpoints&lt;/code&gt; onto. If you choose to do this, it is assumed that you will be starting your own express server and this won&amp;rsquo;t be done by Botmaster. Unless you also specify a &lt;code&gt;server&lt;/code&gt; parameter, &lt;code&gt;botmaster.server&lt;/code&gt; will be &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;server&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;optional&lt;/strong&gt;) an &lt;code&gt;http&lt;/code&gt; server object. It can be accessed via &lt;code&gt;botmaster.server&lt;/code&gt; once instantiated. If passed and using socket.io. This server object will be used as the socker.io server.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;notices info&#34; &gt;&lt;p&gt;Please note, if you are passing in an &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; object to the settings, it is assumed that you are dealing with anything relating to your http server. That is start listening, closing it if necessary etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;notices warning&#34; &gt;&lt;p&gt;If using socket.io (&lt;code&gt;socketio&lt;/code&gt;), you will need to either define BOTH an &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; object and its corresponding &lt;code&gt;server&lt;/code&gt; object in the settings. Or if you would rather botmaster manage this for you, you can define none of them. Alternatively, if you want, say, to have a different http server for your main botmaster app and for socket.io, you can do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;.
.
const socketioSettings = {
  id: &#39;SOME_ID_OF_YOUR_CHOOSING&#39;,
  server: &#39;SOME_HTTP_SERVER_OF_YOURS&#39;, // this server can&#39;t run on port 3000 in this example
};

const botsSettings = [{ telegram: telegramSettings },
                      { messenger: messengerSettings },
                      { twitter: twitterSettings },
                      { slack: slackSettings },
                      { socketio: socketioSettings }];

const botmasterSettings = {
  botsSettings: botsSettings,
}

const botmaster = new Botmaster(botmasterSettings);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, a server will be started under the hood by botmaster using your express. This http server will be a different one from the one used in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;events&#34;&gt;Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botmaster is built on top of the EventEmitter node.js class. Which means it can emit events and most importantly for us here, it can listen onto them. By doing any of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;server running&#39;, (message) =&amp;gt; {
  console.log(message);
});

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  console.log(bot.type);
  console.log(update);
});

botmaster.on(&#39;error&#39;, (bot, err) =&amp;gt; {
  console.log(bot.type);
  console.log(err.stack);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the only four listeners that you can listen onto in botmaster. Let&amp;rsquo;s go though them briefly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;server-running&#34;&gt;server running&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event will be emitted only if you are not managing your own server (i.e. you started botmaster without setting the &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; parameter). It is just here to notify you that the server has been started. You don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need to use it. But you might want to do things at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;update&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really where all the magic happens. Whenever a message (update in Botmaster semantic) is sent into your application. Botmaster will parse it and format it into its [FB Messenger] standard. Along with it, you will get a &lt;code&gt;bot&lt;/code&gt; object which is the underlying object into which the message was sent. Note that the updates are standardized as well as the methods to use from the bot object (i.e. sending a message). Read further down to see how those two objects work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;error&#34;&gt;error&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event is thrown whenever an error internal to Botmaster occurs. I.e. if for some reason a misconfigured message was sent in. Or if some other kind of error occurred directly within Botmaster. It is good to listen onto this event and keep track of potential errors. Also, if you code an error within &lt;code&gt;botmaster.on&lt;/code&gt;, and don&amp;rsquo;t catch it, it will be caught by Botmaster and emitted in to &lt;code&gt;error&lt;/code&gt;. So like this you have full control of what is going on and can log everything straight from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bot-object&#34;&gt;Bot object&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bot objects are really the ones running the show in the Botmaster framework. Your &lt;code&gt;botmaster&lt;/code&gt; object is simply a central point of control for you to manage all of your bots. Botmaster assumes that most of your bots will have a central bit of code that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to replicate for every platform/bot instance. Which should make sense. To drive the point a little further, here is another [perfectly acceptable way] of starting botmaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
const MessengerBot = Botmaster.botTypes.MessengerBot;
.
.
const botmaster = new Botmaster();
.
. // full settings objects omitted for brevity
.
const messengerBot = new MessengerBot(messengerSettings);
const slackBot = new SlackBot(slackSettings);
const twitterBot = new TwitterBot(twitterSettings);
const socketioBot = new SocketioBot(socketioSettings);
const telegramBot = new TelegramBot(telegramSettings);

botmaster.addBot(messengerBot);
botmaster.addBot(slackBot);
botmaster.addBot(twitterBot);
botmaster.addBot(socketioBot);
botmaster.addBot(telegramBot);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the point of botmaster is for developers to do something like this after declaring the botmaster instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  // do stuff with your bot and update here
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can just as well do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;messengerBot.on(&#39;upadte&#39;, (update) =&amp;gt; {
  // do stuff with your messenger bot here
});

// this applies to all the bot objects that would have been declared separately.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; object is the as the botmaster &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; one you would get from that bot. Of course, this code would only apply to your &lt;code&gt;messengerBot&lt;/code&gt; instance and not the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen, bot instances can be accessed directly within an &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; event. Because you might want to act differently on bots of a certain type or log information differently based on type, every bot comes with a &lt;code&gt;bot.type&lt;/code&gt; parameter that is one of: &lt;code&gt;messenger&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;slack&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;twitter&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;socketio&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;telegram&lt;/code&gt; or whatever third-party bot class you might have installed or created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note here, that you can have multiple bot objects for a certain type. I&amp;rsquo;m sure you can find reasons for why you would want to do this. This is important to mention, as you might have, say, 2 bots of type &lt;code&gt;messenger&lt;/code&gt; dealt with via Botmaster. You might want to do platform specific code by doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  if (bot.type === &#39;messenger&#39; {
    // do messenger specific stuff
    return;
  })
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you might want to do bot object specific code. You would do this as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  if (bot.type === &#39;messenger&#39; {
    // do messenger specific stuff
    if (bot.id === &#39;YOUR_BOT_ID&#39;) {// this will be the user id of bot for messenger
      // do bot object specific stuff
      return;
    }
  })
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;notices warning&#34; &gt;&lt;p&gt;Botmaster does not assure you that the &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt; parameter of the &lt;code&gt;bot&lt;/code&gt; object will exist upon instantiation. the &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt; is only assured to be there once an update has been received by the bot. This is because some ids aren&amp;rsquo;t known until botmaster knows &amp;lsquo;who&amp;rsquo; [your bot] the message was sent to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or if you declared your bots and botmaster as in the beginning of this section, you might have done the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
const botmaster = new Botmaster();
.
. // full settings objects omitted for brevity
.
const messengerBot1 = new MessengerBot(messengerSettings1);
const messengerBot2 = new MessengerBot(messengerSettings2);
const slackBot = new SlackBot(slackSettings);
const twitterBot = new TwitterBot(twitterSettings);

botmaster.addBot(messengerBot);
botmaster.addBot(slackBot);
botmaster.addBot(twitterBot);

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  if (bot.type === &#39;messenger&#39; {
    // do messenger bot specific stuff


    if (bot === messengerBot1) { // without using ids
      // do messengerBot1 specific stuff
    }
    return;
  })
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to perform bot object specific code, I recommend declaring your objects in this way rather than the standard way. If you want to perform platform specific way, the standard way is perfectly fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll note quickly that each bot object created comes from one of the various bot classes as seen above. They act in the same way on the surface (because of heavy standardization), but have a few idiosynchrasies here and there. You can read about them all in their own sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also useful to note is that you can access all the bots added to botmaster by doing &lt;code&gt;botmaster.bots&lt;/code&gt;. you can also use &lt;code&gt;botmastet.getBot&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;botmaster.getBots&lt;/code&gt; to get a specific bot (using type or id);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note the &lt;code&gt;addBot&lt;/code&gt; syntax as you can create your own Bot class that extends the &lt;code&gt;Botmaster.botTypes.BaseBot&lt;/code&gt; class. For instance, you might want to create your own class that supports your pre-existing messaging standards. Have a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;working-with-botmaster/writing-a-botmaster-supported-bot-class-readme.md&#34;&gt;working with a botmaster supported bot class &lt;/a&gt; documentation to learn how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;message-update-format&#34;&gt;Message/Update format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standardization is at the heart of Botmaster. The framework was really created for that purpose. This means that messages coming from any platform have to have the same format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to do that, the &lt;strong&gt;Facebook Messenger message format&lt;/strong&gt; was chosen and adopted. This means that when your botmaster object receives an &amp;lsquo;update&amp;rsquo; event from anywhere, you can be sure that it will be of the same format as a similar message that would come from Facebook Messenger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;incoming-update&#34;&gt;Incoming update&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, it would look something like this for a message with an image attachment. Independent of what platform the message comes from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;{
  raw: &amp;lt;platform_specific_raw_update&amp;gt;,
  sender: {
    id: &amp;lt;id_of_sender&amp;gt;
  },
  recipient: {
    id: &amp;lt;id_of_the_recipent&amp;gt; // will typically be the bot&#39;s id
  },
  timestamp: &amp;lt;unix_miliseconds_timestamp&amp;gt;,
  message: {
    mid: &amp;lt;message_id&amp;gt;,
    seq: &amp;lt;message_sequence_id&amp;gt;,
    attachments: [
      {
        type: &#39;image&#39;,
        payload: {
          url: &#39;https://scontent.xx.fbcdn.net/v/.....&#39;
        }
      }
    ]
  }
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows developers to handle these messages in one place only rather than doing it in multiple places. For more info on the various incoming messages formats, read the messenger bot doc on webhooks at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/messenger-platform/webhook-reference/message-received&#34;&gt;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/messenger-platform/webhook-reference/message-received&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, you will only get updates for &lt;code&gt;Messages&lt;/code&gt; (and not delivery, echo notification etc) for all platforms. On Messenger, it is assumed that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to get updates for delivery, read and echo. This can&amp;rsquo;t be turned on at the moment, but will be in later versions as it might be a requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;note-on-attachment-types-and-conversions&#34;&gt;Note on attachment types and conversions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attachment type conversion on incoming updates works as such for &lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Twitter Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Botmaster conversion&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;photo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;video&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;video&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gif&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;video&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;!!!Yes &lt;code&gt;gif&lt;/code&gt; becomes a &lt;code&gt;video&lt;/code&gt;. because Twitter doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually use gifs the way you would expect it to. It simply loops over a short &lt;code&gt;.mp4&lt;/code&gt; video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, here&amp;rsquo;s an important caveat for Twitter bot developers who are receiving attachments. Image links that come in from the Twitter API will be private and not public, which makes using them quite tricky. You might need to make authenticated requests to do so. The twitterBot objects you will receive in the update will have a &lt;code&gt;bot.twit&lt;/code&gt; object. Documentation for how to use this is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ttezel/twit&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving and sending attachments [the Botmaster way] is not yet supported on &lt;strong&gt;Slack&lt;/strong&gt; as of version 2.2.1. However, Slack supports url unfurling (meaning if you send images and other types of media this will be shown in the messages and users won&amp;rsquo;t just see a url). Also, because of how Botmaster is built (don&amp;rsquo;t throw any of the original information from the message away) you can find all the necessary information in the &lt;code&gt;update.raw&lt;/code&gt; object of the update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attachment type conversion works as such for &lt;strong&gt;Telegram&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Telegram Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Botmaster conversion&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;audio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;audio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;voice&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;audio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;photo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;video&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;video&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;venue&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;contact&lt;/code&gt; attachment types aren&amp;rsquo;t supported in Messenger. So in order to deal with them in Botmaster, you will have to look into your &lt;code&gt;update.raw&lt;/code&gt; object which is the standard Telegram update. You will find your contact object in &lt;code&gt;update.raw.contact&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, concerning &lt;code&gt;location&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;venue&lt;/code&gt; attachments. The url received in Botmaster for Telegram is a google maps one with the coordinates as query parameters. It looks something like this: &lt;code&gt;https://maps.google.com/?q=&amp;lt;lat&amp;gt;,&amp;lt;long&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of you will want to use attachments with your &lt;code&gt;socket.io&lt;/code&gt; bots. Because the Botmaster message standard is the Facebook Messenger one, everything is URL based. Which means it is left to the developer to store both incoming and outgoing attachments. A tutorial on how to deal with this will be up soon in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/tutorials&#34;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;outgoing-messages&#34;&gt;Outgoing messages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, outgoing messages are expected to be formatted like messages the Messenger platform would expect. They will typically look something like this for a text message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const message = {
  recipient: {
    id: update.sender.id,
  },
  message: {
    text: &#39;Some arbitrary text of yours&#39;
  },
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you would use this as such in code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  const message = {
    recipient: {
      id: update.sender.id,
    },
    message: {
      text: &#39;Some arbitrary text of yours&#39;
    },
  };
  bot.sendMessage(message);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the &lt;code&gt;sendMessage&lt;/code&gt; method used is used directly from the bot object and not using the botmaster one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you might not always want to code in a complex json object just to send in a simple text message or photo attachment, Botmaster comes with a few helper methods that can be used to send messages with less code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bot.sendMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;message&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;an object without the recipient part. In the previous example, it would be &lt;code&gt;message.message&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;recipientId&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a string representing the id of the user to whom you want to send the message.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bot.sendTextMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;text&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;just a string with the text you want to send to your user&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;recipientId&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a string representing the id of the user to whom you want to send the message.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically used like so to send a text message to the user who just spoke to the bot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.sendTextMessageTo(&#39;something super important&#39;, update.sender.id);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bot.reply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;update&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;an update object with a valid &lt;code&gt;update.sender.id&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;text&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;just a string with the text you want to send to your user&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is is typically used like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;something super important!&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;attachments&#34;&gt;Attachments&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bot.sendAttachmentTo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll note here really quickly that Messenger only takes in urls for file attachment (image, video, audio, file). Most other platforms don&amp;rsquo;t support sending attachments in this way. So we fall back to sending the url in text which really results in a very similar output. Same goes for Twitter that doesn&amp;rsquo;t support attachments at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;attachment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a valid Messenger style attachment. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/messenger-platform/send-api-reference&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more on that.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;recipientId&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a string representing the id of the user to whom you want to send the message.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the general attachment sending method that will always work for Messenger but not necessarily for other platforms as Facebook Messenger supports all sorts of attachments that other platforms don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily support. So beware when using it. To assure your attachment will be sent to all platforms, use &lt;code&gt;bot.sendAttachmentFromURLTo&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is typically used as such for sending an image url.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  const attachment = {
    type: &#39;image&#39;
    payload: {
      url: &amp;quot;some image url you&#39;ve got&amp;quot;,
    },
  };
  bot.sendAttachment(attachment, update.sender.id);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bot.sendAttachmentFromURLTo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just easier to use this to send standard url attachments. And URL attachments if used properly should work on all out-of-the-box platforms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;type&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;string representing the type of attachment (audio, video, image or file)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;url&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;the url to your file&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;recipientId&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a string representing the id of the user to whom you want to send the message.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is typically used as such for sending an image url.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.sendAttachment(&#39;image&#39;, &amp;quot;some image url you&#39;ve got&amp;quot;, update.sender.id);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bot.sendIsTypingMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To indicate that something is happening on your bots end, you can show your users that the bot is &amp;lsquo;working&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;typing&amp;rsquo; something. to do so, simply invoke sendIsTypingMessageTo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;recipientId&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a string representing the id of the user to whom you want to send the message.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is used as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
    bot.sendIsTypingMessageTo(update.sender.id);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will only send a request to the platforms that support it. If unsupported, nothing will happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;buttons&#34;&gt;Buttons&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buttons will almost surely be part of your bot. Botmaster provides a method that will send what is assumed to be a decent way to display buttons throughout all platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bot.sendDefaultButtonMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Argument&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;buttonTitles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;array of button titles (no longer than 10 in size).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;recipientId&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;a string representing the id of the user to whom you want to send the message.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;textOrAttachment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;optional&lt;/strong&gt;) a string or an attachment object similar to the ones required in &lt;code&gt;bot.sendAttachmentTo&lt;/code&gt;. This is meant to provide context to the buttons. I.e. why are there buttons here. A piece of text or an attachment could detail that. If not provided,  text will be added that reads: &amp;lsquo;Please select one of:&amp;lsquo;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function defaults to sending &lt;code&gt;quick_replies&lt;/code&gt; in Messenger, setting &lt;code&gt;Keyboard buttons&lt;/code&gt; in Telegram, buttons in Slack and simply prints button titles one on each line in Twitter as it doesn&amp;rsquo;t support buttons. The user is expecting to type in their choice in Twitter. In the socketio implementation, the front-end/app developer is expected to write the code that would display the buttons on their front-end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-botmaster-with-your-own-express-app&#34;&gt;Using Botmaster with your own express() app&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example on how to do so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const express = require(&#39;express&#39;);
const app = express();
const port = 3000;

const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);

const telegramSettings = {
  credentials: {
    authToken: process.env.TELEGRAM_TEST_TOKEN,
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook1234/&#39;,
};

const messengerSettings = {
  credentials: {
    verifyToken: process.env.MESSENGER_VERIFY_TOKEN,
    pageToken: process.env.MESSENGER_PAGE_TOKEN,
    fbAppSecret: process.env.FACEBOOK_APP_SECRET,
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook1234/&#39;,
};

const botsSettings = [{ telegram: telegramSettings },
                      { messenger: messengerSettings }];

const botmasterSettings = {
  botsSettings: botsSettings,
  app: app,
}

const botmaster = new Botmaster(botmasterSettings);

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.sendMessage({
    recipient: {
      id: update.sender.id,
    },
    message: {
      text: &#39;Well right back at you!&#39;,
    },
  });
});

console.log(`Loading App`);
// start server on the specified port and binding host
app.listen(port, &#39;0.0.0.0&#39;, () =&amp;gt; {
  // print a message when the server starts listening
  console.log(`Running App on port: ${port}`);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installation</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 18:46:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/installation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Make sure you have &lt;a href=&#34;https://nodejs.org/en/&#34;&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt; and npm installed on your machine. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, I recommend using nvm to manage your node versions. Find out more about it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/creationix/nvm/blob/master/README.markdown&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have node, create a new project directory and go into it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;mkdir my_botmaster_project &amp;amp;&amp;amp; cd my_botmaster_project
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you initialize a node project in the new directory and going through the prompt by doing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;npm init
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, install the botmaster npm package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;npm install --save botmaster
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That should do!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing your Own Bot Class</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/writing-your-own-bot-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 18:16:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/writing-your-own-bot-class/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bot-classes&#34;&gt;Bot classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following assumes that you have read the main documentation in &amp;ldquo;getting started&amp;rdquo; and in &amp;ldquo;botmaster basics&amp;rdquo;. A general understand of how Botmaster and more generally how chatbots work is also assumed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of that, we will pick up right from there and start looking into the bot classes Botmaster comes bundled with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botmaster makes five usable bot classes available to developers out of the box. &lt;code&gt;MessengerBot&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;SlackBot&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;SocketioBot&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;TelegramBot&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;TwitterBot&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you can instantiate a new &lt;code&gt;MessengerBot&lt;/code&gt; object as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
const MessengerBot = Botmaster.botTypes.MessengerBot;

const messengerSettings = {
  credentials: {
    verifyToken: &#39;YOUR verifyToken&#39;,
    pageToken: &#39;YOUR pageToken&#39;,
    fbAppSecret: &#39;YOUR fbAppSecret&#39;
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook1234&#39;,
};

const messengerBot = new MessengerBot(messengerSettings);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to get updates from Messenger, you would then be expected to mount your bot&amp;rsquo;s express mini-app &lt;code&gt;messengerBot.app&lt;/code&gt; onto your own express &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; by doing something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const app = require(&#39;express&#39;)();
app.use(&#39;/&#39;, messengerBot.app);
app.listen(3000, function() {});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will mount your bot onto: &lt;code&gt;https://Your_Domain_Name/webhook1234&lt;/code&gt;. Note how the bot type &lt;strong&gt;is not&lt;/strong&gt; part of the URL here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-botmaster-objects-and-bot-objects-work-together&#34;&gt;Making Botmaster objects and bot objects work together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/botmaster-basics&#34;&gt;botmaster basics&lt;/a&gt; sectio nwe saw how botmaster objects return a bot object along with every update it receives. I.e. something like this happens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  console.log(bot.type);
  console.log(update);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also saw in the last section how to setup a bot using its own bot class. Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at how to use this bot inside of a botmaster object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, we create a botmaster object. This one supports Twitter and Telegram, but not Messenger. We create it as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);

const twitterSettings = {
    consumerKey: &#39;YOUR consumerKey&#39;,
    consumerSecret: &#39;YOUR consumerSecret&#39;,
    accessToken: &#39;YOUR accessToken&#39;,
    accessTokenSecret: &#39;YOUR accessTokenSecret&#39;,
  }
}

const telegramSettings = {
  credentials: {
    authToken: &#39;YOUR authToken&#39;,
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook1234/&#39;,
};

const botsSettings = [{ twitter: twitterSettings },
                      { telegram: telegramSettings }];

const botmasterSettings = { botsSettings: botsSettings };

const botmaster = new Botmaster(botmasterSettings);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example the &lt;code&gt;botmaster&lt;/code&gt; object will start a new &lt;code&gt;express()&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; server running locally on port &lt;code&gt;3000&lt;/code&gt; as expected by default (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster/botmaster-basics/#using-botmaster-with-your-own-express-app&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see how to change that). However, we later might want to add to botmaster the object we created in the first section, namely, &lt;code&gt;messengerBot&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can achieve this by doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;botmaster.addBot(messengerBot);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will mount your bot onto: &lt;code&gt;https://Your_Domain_Name/messenger/webhook1234&lt;/code&gt;. Note how the bot type &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; part of the endpoint here. This is because the Botmaster class assumes that you want your endpoint to be mounted onto its botType.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will then get updates from the botmaster object as if you had instantiated it with the messenger settings too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What this means is that any bot class that follows a  certain set of rules will be able to be added to a botmaster object.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-your-own-bot-classes&#34;&gt;Creating your own bot classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before defining the rules that have to be respected in order to write a Botmaster compatible bot class let&amp;rsquo;s look at the constructor of one of the existing one, &lt;code&gt;TelegramBot&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;constructor-settings&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#constructor(settings)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;class TelegramBot extends BaseBot {

  constructor(settings) {
    super(settings);
    this.type = &#39;telegram&#39;;
    this.requiresWebhook = true;
    this.requiredCredentials = [&#39;authToken&#39;];

    this.__applySettings(settings);
    .
    .
    .
    this.__createMountPoints();
  }

 }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look into this line by line. The first line reads &lt;code&gt;super(settings)&lt;/code&gt;. Which of course just means it calls the constructor of &lt;code&gt;TelegramBot&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s superclass, namely, &lt;code&gt;BaseBot&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;BaseBot&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s constructor doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually do anything fancy a part from calling its own superclass&amp;rsquo;s constructor and setting a few default values [as pointers for you, the developer]. BaseBot calls its own superclass&amp;rsquo;s constructor as it inherits from node.js&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;EventEmitter&lt;/code&gt; which will allow your bot&amp;rsquo;s classes to listen to events as well as emit them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following three lines setup some important values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;this.type&lt;/code&gt;: the type of bot that is being instantiated. It&amp;rsquo;s important to specify that as developers might want to condition some code on the type of bot you are writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;this.requiresWebhook&lt;/code&gt;: whether the bot requires webhooks. If the platform you are coding for requires webhooks, you will be expected to set a &lt;code&gt;this.app&lt;/code&gt; variable at some point in the setup. We&amp;rsquo;ll look into this when we have a look at what the &lt;code&gt;this.__createMountPoints();&lt;/code&gt; does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;this.requiredCredentials&lt;/code&gt;: sets up an array of credentials that are expected to be defined for the platform you are coding your class for. Telegram only takes in 1, so we just have an array with the value &lt;code&gt;&#39;authToken&#39;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;applysettings-settings&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#__applySettings(settings)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next line calls the &lt;code&gt;this.__applySettings(settings)&lt;/code&gt; function. This function is implemented in BaseBot and will just make sure that the settings passed on to the bot constructor are valid with respect to the parameters you defined. You should always call this function directly after setting the three [or more or less depending on your bot] parameters specific to the platform you are coding for. If valid, the settings will then be applied to the bot object. e.g. &lt;code&gt;this.webhookEndpoint&lt;/code&gt; will be set to &lt;code&gt;settings.webhookEndpoint&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;createmountpoints&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#__createMountPoints()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last line of our controller makes a call to &lt;code&gt;this.__createMountPoints();&lt;/code&gt;. This line should only be present if your bot class requires webhooks. If this is the case, you will be expected to define a class member function that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;  __createMountPoints() {
    this.app = express();
    // for parsing application/json
    this.app.use(bodyParser.json());
    // for parsing application/x-www-form-urlencoded
    this.app.use(bodyParser.urlencoded({ extended: true }));

    this.app.post(this.webhookEndpoint, (req, res) =&amp;gt; {
      this.__formatUpdate(req.body)

      .then((update) =&amp;gt; {
        this.__emitUpdate(update);
      }, (err) =&amp;gt; {
        err.message = `Error in __formatUpdate &amp;quot;${err.message}&amp;quot;. Please report this.`;
        this.emit(&#39;error&#39;, err);
      });

      // just letting telegram know we got the update
      res.sendStatus(200);
    });
  }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very importantly, this function creates an express router &lt;code&gt;this.app&lt;/code&gt; that will be mounted onto the main &lt;code&gt;app&lt;/code&gt; router from the botmaster object if &lt;code&gt;botmaster.addBot&lt;/code&gt; is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It then sets up the post endpoint that listens onto &lt;code&gt;this.webhookEnpoint&lt;/code&gt;. No further assumption is made here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that you might have another function that needs to be called at this point. For instance, in the &lt;code&gt;socketioBot&lt;/code&gt; class, I make a call to: &lt;code&gt;this.__setupSocketioServer();&lt;/code&gt; and that function looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;__setupSocketioServer() {
  this.ioServer = io(this.server);

  this.ioServer.on(&#39;connection&#39;, (socket) =&amp;gt; {
    socket.join(SocketioBot.__getBotmasteruserId(socket));

    socket.on(&#39;message&#39;, (message) =&amp;gt; {
      // just broadcast the message to other connected clients with same user id
      const botmasterUserId = SocketioBot.__getBotmasteruserId(socket);
      socket.broadcast.to(botmasterUserId).emit(&#39;own message&#39;, message);
      // console.log(JSON.stringify(socket.rooms, null, 2));
      const rawUpdate = message;
      try {
        rawUpdate.socket = socket;
      } catch (err) {
        err.message = `ERROR: &amp;quot;Expected JSON object but got &#39;${typeof message}&#39; ${message} instead&amp;quot;`;
        return this.emit(&#39;error&#39;, err);
      }
      const update = this.__formatUpdate(rawUpdate, botmasterUserId);
      return this.__emitUpdate(update);
    });
  });
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t explain what is going on here as it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary for building your own Bot class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setbotidifnotset-update&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#__setBotIdIfNotSet(update)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to help you identify between bots of different types, you will want each bot instance to have a &lt;code&gt;this.id&lt;/code&gt; value. This will often be the same as &lt;code&gt;update.recipient.id&lt;/code&gt; when getting updates. But not always (for instance with socket.io bots). If these aren&amp;rsquo;t set upon instantiation as with Facebook Messenger bots, you can write a function like this that gets called upon receiving a message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a good default implementation used in many of botmaster&amp;rsquo;s internal bot types:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;__setBotIdIfNotSet(update) {
  if (!this.id) {
  	this.id = update.recipient.id;
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;formatupdate-rawupdate&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#__formatUpdate(rawUpdate)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although you can technically handle the body of the request as you wish. In our &lt;code&gt;__createMountPoints&lt;/code&gt; example here (from TelegramBot code), we make a call to the &lt;code&gt;__formatUpdate&lt;/code&gt; function with the body of the request.
It would make sense for you to do so for consistency and because it has to be defined if you want your bot class to eventually be referenced in the Botmaster project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This function is expected to transform the &lt;code&gt;rawUpdate&lt;/code&gt; into an object which is of the format of Messenger updates, while having an &lt;code&gt;update.raw&lt;/code&gt; bit that references that &lt;code&gt;rawUpdate&lt;/code&gt; received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, it would look something like this for a message with an image attachment. Independent of what platform the message comes from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;{
  raw: &amp;lt;platform_specific_raw_update&amp;gt;,
  sender: {
    id: &amp;lt;id_of_sender&amp;gt;
  },
  recipient: {
    id: &amp;lt;id_of_the_recipent&amp;gt; // will typically be the bot&#39;s id
  },
  timestamp: &amp;lt;unix_miliseconds_timestamp&amp;gt;,
  message: {
    mid: &amp;lt;message_id&amp;gt;,
    seq: &amp;lt;message_sequence_id&amp;gt;,
    attachments: [
      {
        type: &#39;image&#39;,
        payload: {
          url: &#39;https://scontent.xx.fbcdn.net/v/.....&#39;
        }
      }
    ]
  }
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your function should return the update object(or a promise that resolves a formatted update object) in order to then call &lt;code&gt;__emitUpdate&lt;/code&gt; with it as a parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;emitupdate-update&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#__emitUpdate(update)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;code&gt;__applySettings&lt;/code&gt;, this method is implemented in &lt;code&gt;BaseBot&lt;/code&gt;. It handles errors, calling the &lt;code&gt;incoming&lt;/code&gt; middleware stack, and most importantly, actually calling &lt;code&gt;this.emit(update)&lt;/code&gt; to emit the actual update. You can overwrite this method if you wish, but in its current state, it handles the most important cases you will want to deal with. You will however need to call it with your formatted update object as a parameter in order to actually get the update object in a &lt;code&gt;bot.on(&#39;update&#39;, callback)&lt;/code&gt; block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sendmessage-message&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#__sendMessage(message)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All previous methods had either something to do with object instantiation or with incoming messages. We&amp;rsquo;ll now have a look at what needs to be done within your bot class to send messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;__sendMessage&lt;/code&gt; method needs to be implemented. The method should take in a Messenger style message and send a formatted message to the bot platform. It should return a &lt;code&gt;Promise&lt;/code&gt; that resolves to something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;  {
   raw: rawBody,
   recipient_id: &amp;lt;id_of_user&amp;gt;,
   message_id: &amp;lt;message_id_of_what_was_just_sent&amp;gt;
  }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that this be a promise and not a callback. Although developers using Botmaster can use &lt;code&gt;sendMessage&lt;/code&gt; type methods with callbacks. The internals of Botmaster use Promises and therefore, so should your bot class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that the &lt;code&gt;BaseBot&lt;/code&gt; superclass defines a set of methods that allow developers to more easily send messages to all platforms without having to build the whole Messenger compatible object themselves. These methods are the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sendMessage&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;sendMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;sendTextMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;reply&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;sendAttachmentTo&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;sendAttachmentFromURLTo&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;sendDefaultButtonMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;sendIsTypingMessageTo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these methods will convert a developer specified input into a Facebook Messenger compatible message that will be called as a parameter to &lt;code&gt;__sendMessage&lt;/code&gt;. That is, they all eventually will call your &lt;code&gt;__sendMessage&lt;/code&gt; method. You can however overwrite them if need be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;formatoutgoingmessage-message&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#__formatOutgoingMessage(message)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your &lt;code&gt;sendMessage&lt;/code&gt; method is expected to call a &lt;code&gt;__formatOutgoingMessage(message)&lt;/code&gt; method that will format the Messenger style message into one that is compatible with the platform you are coding your bot class for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can have a look at the ones defined in the &lt;code&gt;TelegramBot&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;TwitterBot&lt;/code&gt; classes for inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-this-really-all-there-is-to-it&#34;&gt;Is this really all there is to it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it is! These few basic steps are the steps that should be followed in order to build your own bot classes. Nothing more is required. Of course, formatting the incoming updates and the outgoing messages won&amp;rsquo;t always be as trivial as we&amp;rsquo;d wish, but this guide should help you into doing this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickstart</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/quickstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 21:39:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/quickstart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you already know your credentials for the platforms you want to be supporting in your project the following code will help you get started&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;
// settings stuff
const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);

const messengerSettings = {
  credentials: {
    verifyToken: &#39;YOUR verifyToken&#39;,
    pageToken: &#39;YOUR pageToken&#39;,
    fbAppSecret: &#39;YOUR fbAppSecret&#39;,
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook1234&#39;, // botmaster will mount this webhook on https://Your_Domain_Name/messenger/webhook1234
};

const twitterSettings = {
  credentials: {
    consumerKey: &#39;YOUR consumerKey&#39;,
    consumerSecret: &#39;YOUR consumerSecret&#39;,
    accessToken: &#39;YOUR accessToken&#39;,
    accessTokenSecret: &#39;YOUR accessTokenSecret&#39;,
  }
}

const telegramSettings = {
  credentials: {
    authToken: &#39;YOUR authToken&#39;,
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook1234/&#39;,
};

const slackSettings = {
  credentials: {
    clientId: &#39;YOUR app client ID&#39;,
    clientSecret: &#39;YOUR app client secret&#39;,
    verificationToken: &#39;YOUR app verification Token&#39;,
    landingPageURL: &#39;YOUR landing page URL&#39; // users will be redirected there after adding your bot app to slack. If not set, they will be redirected to their standard slack chats.
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook&#39;,
  storeTeamInfoInFile: true,
};

const socketioSettings = {
  id: &#39;SOME_ID_OF_YOUR_CHOOSING&#39;,
};

const botsSettings = [{ telegram: telegramSettings },
                      { messenger: messengerSettings },
                      { twitter: twitterSettings },
                      { slack: slackSettings },
                      { socketio: socketioSettings }];

const botmasterSettings = {
  botsSettings: botsSettings,
  // by default botmaster will start an express server that listens on port 3000
  // you can pass in a port argument here to change this default setting:
  port: 3001,
}

const botmaster = new Botmaster(botmasterSettings);

// actual code
botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.sendTextMessageTo(&#39;Right back at you!&#39;, update.sender.id);
});

botmaster.on(&#39;error&#39;, (bot, err) =&amp;gt; {
  console.log(err.stack);
  console.log(&#39;there was an error&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting set up</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/getting-set-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/getting-set-up/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In order to instantiate a &lt;code&gt;Botmaster&lt;/code&gt; object, you need to pass it some settings in the form of an object. These settings look like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const botmasterSettings = {
  botsSettings: botsSettings, // see below for a definition of botsSettings
  app: app, // optional, an express app object if you are running your own server
  server: server, // optional, an http server object (used if using socket.io)
  port: port, // optional, only used if &amp;quot;app&amp;quot; is not defined. Defaults t0 3000 in that case
  sessionStore: sessionStore // optional. Define if you will be dealing with sessions
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/working-with-botmaster&#34;&gt;Working with Botmaster&lt;/a&gt; for a more formal definition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;botsSettings&lt;/code&gt; look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const botsSettings = [{ messenger: messengerSettings },
                      { twitter: twitterSettings },
                      { twitter: otherTwitterSettings }];
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I.e. it is an array of single key objects. Where you specify the &lt;strong&gt;type as the key&lt;/strong&gt; of each object and the &lt;strong&gt;settings as the value&lt;/strong&gt;. Here I show that you can define multiple bots of the same type at once (twitter ones in this example). As you surely guessed, each different platform will expect different credentials. So platform specific settings will differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have those &lt;code&gt;botmasterSettings&lt;/code&gt;, you can go on and instantiate a &lt;code&gt;Botmaster&lt;/code&gt; object. This looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const botmaster = new Botmaster(botmasterSettings);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know what you&amp;rsquo;re thinking: &amp;ldquo;but how do I get these &lt;code&gt;messengerSettings&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;twitterSettings&lt;/code&gt; or other ones?&amp;rdquo; Well, I cover all of those in the following pages.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facebook Messenger Setup</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/messenger-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:24:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/messenger-setup/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);

const messengerSettings = {
  credentials: {
    verifyToken: &#39;YOUR verifyToken&#39;,
    pageToken: &#39;YOUR pageToken&#39;,
    fbAppSecret: &#39;YOUR fbAppSecret&#39;,
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhook1234&#39;,
};

const botsSettings = [{ messenger: messengerSettings }];

const botmaster = new Botmaster({ botsSettings });

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;Right back at you&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-your-credentials&#34;&gt;Getting your Credentials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t already have these, follow the steps &lt;strong&gt;1-4&lt;/strong&gt; on the Facebook Messenger guide:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/messenger-platform/guides/quick-start&#34;&gt;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/messenger-platform/guides/quick-start&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;step 2&lt;/strong&gt;, where you setup your webhook, no need to code anything. Just specify the webhook, enter any secure string you want as a verify token(&lt;code&gt;verifyToken&lt;/code&gt;) and copy that value in the settings object. Also, click on whichever message [those are &amp;ldquo;update&amp;rdquo;s using botmaster semantics] type you want to receive from Messenger (&lt;code&gt;message_deliveries&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;messages&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;message_postbacks&lt;/code&gt; etc&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find your Facebook App Secret (&lt;code&gt;fbAppSecret&lt;/code&gt;), navigate to your apps dashboard and under &lt;code&gt;App Secret&lt;/code&gt; click show, enter your password if prompted and then there it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;webhooks&#34;&gt;Webhooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;notices note&#34; &gt;&lt;p&gt;If you are not too sure how webhooks work and/or how to get them to run locally, go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/webhooks&#34;&gt;webhooks&lt;/a&gt; to read some more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slack Setup</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/slack-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 23:01:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/slack-setup/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);

const slackSettings = {
  credentials: {
    clientId: &#39;YOUR app client ID&#39;,
    clientSecret: &#39;YOUR app client secret&#39;,
    verificationToken: &#39;YOUR app verification Token&#39;
  },
  webhookEndpoint: &#39;/webhookd24sr34se&#39;,
  storeTeamInfoInFile: true,
};

const botsSettings = [{ slack: slackSettings }];

const botmaster = new Botmaster({ botsSettings });

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;Right back at you&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-botmaster-slack-bot&#34;&gt;The Botmaster Slack bot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Slack works slightly differently from the other platforms covered in the core Botmaster package, I will briefly explain here what your botmaster Slack bot will be exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you surely know, Slack is a product that enables team members to communicate easily with one another. because of that, one team member can&amp;rsquo;t just &amp;ldquo;add&amp;rdquo; a bot for herself in the same way one would in Facebook Messenger or Telegram or other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams can either build a bot that will only live within their own slack team. Or they can package a bot in a Slack app that &amp;ldquo;packages&amp;rdquo; the bot.
Admin team members can add support for a bot (by installing an App that packages said bot) and then team members can start communicating with it as they would with another team member. At this point, they would be communicating with what is known as, in Slack semantics, a &lt;strong&gt;bot user&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;slackSettings&lt;/code&gt; object is required to allow us to communicate to end users via this &lt;strong&gt;bot user&lt;/strong&gt; that needs to be set up on Slack&amp;rsquo;s end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;botmaster-slack-bot-mini-tutorial&#34;&gt;Botmaster Slack bot mini-tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following these steps, you will have a fully functional Slack bot using botmaster that can then be edited as wanted. This mini-tutorial uses localtunnel to expose one of your ports to the world. see why you might want to use this and how to install and setup localtunnel &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/webhooks#localtunnel&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;for your local botmaster project. You can use ngrok or any other service you know or find suitable and achieve the same result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;create-an-app&#34;&gt;Create an app&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate to: &lt;a href=&#34;https://api.slack.com/apps&#34;&gt;https://api.slack.com/apps&lt;/a&gt; and make sure you are signed in. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t you will be redirected to your team&amp;rsquo;s slack once logged in and will need to go back to the mentioned link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;create new App&lt;/strong&gt; button and enter any App Name you want. This won&amp;rsquo;t be the name of the &lt;strong&gt;bot user&lt;/strong&gt;. However, the name should ideally be related to your bot user so as not to confuse your users. For instance, if your bot user will be called &lt;em&gt;my_super_bot&lt;/em&gt;, calling the app something like &lt;em&gt;My Super Bot App&lt;/em&gt; would make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;get-your-first-credentials&#34;&gt;Get your first credentials&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this page you were redirected to, you will find an &lt;em&gt;App credentials&lt;/em&gt; section. Both your Client ID (&lt;code&gt;clientId&lt;/code&gt; in Botmaster) and your Client Secret (&lt;code&gt;clientSecret&lt;/code&gt; in Botmaster) are here. Take note of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;setup-your-app-s-oauth-webhook&#34;&gt;Setup Your App&amp;rsquo;s OAuth Webhook&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to know anything about OAuth to complete this step. Just know that this URL will be called when people are installing/authorizing your app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the left panel, click on the &lt;strong&gt;OAuth &amp;amp; Permissions&lt;/strong&gt; tab and enter your webhook in the &lt;strong&gt;Redirect URL(s)&lt;/strong&gt; field as shown here:
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/images/slack_setup_1.png?width=90%&#34; alt=&#34;Slack Setup 1&#34; /&gt;
This URL has to be of the form: &lt;strong&gt;https://&amp;lt;your_base_url&amp;gt;/slack/&amp;lt;webhookEndpoint&amp;gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt; I am using localtunnel to test the bot locally, and started localtunnel by running the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;  lt -p 3000 -s botmastersubdomain
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would set my Redirect URL(s) to: &lt;code&gt;https://botmastersubdomain.localtunnel.me/slack/webhookd24sr34se&lt;/code&gt; (based on the &lt;code&gt;webhookEnpoint&lt;/code&gt; set in my &lt;code&gt;slackSettings&lt;/code&gt; at the top of this page). Click on &lt;strong&gt;Save Changes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;add-a-bot-user&#34;&gt;Add a Bot User&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;strong&gt;Bot Users&lt;/strong&gt; and click on the &lt;strong&gt;Add a Bot User&lt;/strong&gt; button. Select a name for your bot (e.g. my_super_bot) and click the &lt;strong&gt;Add Bot User&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;get-the-rest-of-your-credentials&#34;&gt;Get the rest of your credentials&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate to the &lt;strong&gt;Event Subscriptions&lt;/strong&gt; tab and click on the toggle button in the to right corner to &lt;strong&gt;on&lt;/strong&gt;. Then in the &lt;strong&gt;Request URL&lt;/strong&gt; field that pops up, enter the same URL as in step 4. &lt;strong&gt;You will get an error&lt;/strong&gt;. This is normal and is due to two reasons. Firstly, we don&amp;rsquo;t actually have an app started and listening at the mentioned URL and secondly because even if we did, we don&amp;rsquo;t have our App&amp;rsquo;s verification Token. Let&amp;rsquo;s fix this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate back to &lt;strong&gt;Basic Information&lt;/strong&gt; and note that you now have a &lt;strong&gt;Verification Token&lt;/strong&gt; in the App Credentials box. Take note of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;start-your-botmaster-app-locally&#34;&gt;Start your Botmaster App Locally&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start your botmaster app in any project folder you might want (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/installation&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you haven&amp;rsquo;t installed botmaster yet). To start the botmaster project, you&amp;rsquo;ll want to create an &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; file with the contents from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/getting-started/slack-setup/#code&#34;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; at the top of this page in the root of your project folder. Replace the credentials with the ones you have gathered. Run &lt;code&gt;node app.js&lt;/code&gt; to start the app. Let&amp;rsquo;s now expose out bot to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the webhook to work locally, you&amp;rsquo;ll now need to make sure you&amp;rsquo;ve started localtunnel. If you are doing all of that from a server that already has a Domain Name, you won&amp;rsquo;t need to do this. But I am assuming most people are doing this from their local computer. so in the command line, run something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;lt -p 3000 -s &amp;lt;wanted_base_url_for_your_bot&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;setup-your-app-s-events-and-events-webhook&#34;&gt;Setup Your App&amp;rsquo;s Events and Events Webhook&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go back to the &lt;strong&gt;Event subscription&lt;/strong&gt; page and enter your webhook url again. This should now work and look something like this: &lt;img src=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/images/slack_setup_2.png?width=90%&#34; alt=&#34;Slack Setup 2&#34; /&gt; Scroll down and click on &lt;strong&gt;Add Bot User Events&lt;/strong&gt;. At the minimum, add the following events:
    * message.ipm
    * message.channels
    * message.im
    * message.groups
Click &lt;strong&gt;Save Changes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;install-your-slack-app&#34;&gt;Install your Slack App&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re almost done here. We need a way to install our app to test it out. This is done via what is called a &lt;strong&gt;Slack button&lt;/strong&gt;. because botmaster manages all the nitty-gritty parts of this process, all you need to do is create a &lt;code&gt;views&lt;/code&gt; folder in your project folder and create an &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file in this views folder with the following contents&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;https://slack.com/oauth/authorize?scope=bot&amp;amp;client_id=YOUR_APP_CLIENT_ID&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;img alt=&amp;quot;Add to Slack&amp;quot; height=&amp;quot;40&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;139&amp;quot;
  src=&amp;quot;https://platform.slack-edge.com/img/add_to_slack.png&amp;quot;
  srcset=&amp;quot;https://platform.slack-edge.com/img/add_to_slack.png 1x,
          https://platform.slack-edge.com/img/add_to_slack@2x.png 2x&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that you&amp;rsquo;ll need to replace &lt;strong&gt;YOUR_APP_CLIENT_ID&lt;/strong&gt; in the href with your own. You definitely don&amp;rsquo;t want to put in your client secret here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;try-out-your-bot&#34;&gt;Try out your bot!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming your botmaster app and localtunnel are still running, open your &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file (not in a text editor, but actually in a browser) by double clicking on it. Authorize your newly created app to add it to your team. You should now be redirected to your teams slack and be able to chat to your bot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;make-your-bot-available-to-the-world&#34;&gt;Make your Bot Available to the World&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might actually want to allow others to install your app by using the Slack Button. However, to do so you will need to host it somewhere. We&amp;rsquo;ll take advantage of the fact that botmaster uses express.js under the hood and edit our app.js file to look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
const express = require(&#39;express&#39;); // added
.
.
.
const botmaster = new Botmaster({ botsSettings });
botmaster.app.use(express.static(__dirname + &#39;/views&#39;)); //added
// or if you don&#39;t want it at the root of your app, add this:
botmaster.app.use(&#39;/slack&#39;, express.static(__dirname + &#39;/views&#39;)); // added

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;Right back at you&#39;);
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to add either one of the &lt;code&gt;botmaster.app.use...&lt;/code&gt; lines.
If you pick the first one, navigate to your URL (&lt;code&gt;https://botmastersubdomain.localtunnel.me/&lt;/code&gt; for this example) and you will see the button.
If your pick the second one, navigate to your sub URL (&lt;code&gt;https://botmastersubdomain.localtunnel.me/slack&lt;/code&gt; for this example) to see the Slack button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;webhooks&#34;&gt;Webhooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as with any other platform using Webhooks, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to update these to your production Domain Name once you deploy your code to production. And in a more general sense, if you are still unsure how webhooks work within the botmaster framework, go &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/webhooks&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socket.io Setup</title>
      <link>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/socketio-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 18:18:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/socketio-setup/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;server&#34;&gt;Server&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);

const socketioSettings = {
  id: &#39;SOME_BOT_ID_OF_YOUR_CHOOSING&#39;,
};

const botsSettings = [{ socketio: socketioSettings }];

const botmaster = new Botmaster({ botsSettings });

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;Right back at you&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;client&#34;&gt;Client&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const io = require(&#39;socket.io-client&#39;);

const socket = io(&amp;quot;ws://localhost:4000&amp;quot;);

socket.on(&#39;connect&#39;, function() {
  const message = {
    text: &#39;Hey there botmaster!&#39;
  };

  socket.send(JSON.stringify(message));
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-botmaster-socket-io-bot&#34;&gt;The Botmaster Socket.io bot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socket.io is a great library that allows developers to write apps using webSockets (with fallbacks to http long-polling and others when webSockets aren&amp;rsquo;t available in the client). You can read more about it on their own website here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://socket.io&#34;&gt;http://socket.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you might want to have a bot that not only works on some platform but also on your own webapp/app, support for socket.io was added to the Botmaster core. Although Socket.io enables developers to use their technology in a bunch of different applications, the fact that you want to use it in Botmaster means that you want to handle 1-1 conversations between users and your bot (managed by botmaster).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve never used both botmaster and socket.io, It&amp;rsquo;s probably still pretty unclear how all of this fits in together. Hopefully the next section will help you understand and get started with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;botmaster-socket-io-bot-mini-tutorial&#34;&gt;Botmaster Socket.io bot mini-tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By following these steps, you will have a fully functional Socket.io bot using botmaster. The client will live in a tiny web-page. The point of this tutorial is to get you started so that you can develop it further in any way you wish. This is completely based on the socket.io web &amp;ldquo;get started&amp;rdquo; guide found here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://socket.io/get-started/chat/&#34;&gt;http://socket.io/get-started/chat/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;server-1&#34;&gt;Server&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After making sure that we have a project folder with a node.js project initialised and the botmaster package in it as per the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/getting-started/installation&#34;&gt;installation&lt;/a&gt; guide.
We want to make sure botmaster is setup and make sure that messages coming from a websocket connection are received. So in our poject folder, in our &lt;code&gt;app.js&lt;/code&gt; file, we simply copy the code found at the top of this page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);

const socketioSettings = {
  id: &#39;SOME_ID_OF_YOUR_CHOOSING&#39;,
};

const botsSettings = [{ socketio: socketioSettings }];

const botmaster = new Botmaster({ botsSettings });

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;Right back at you&#39;);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will need to add a couple of lines to this code because we will be serving a webpage from our server. Not just listening on for botmaster messages. To do so, we take advantage of the fact that botmaster is built on top of express and that. We also assume that we will be serving our static assets (the components of our webpage) from a folder called &amp;lsquo;public&amp;rsquo; within our project directory. Our updated code looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;const Botmaster = require(&#39;botmaster&#39;);
const express = require(&#39;express&#39;); //added

const socketioSettings = {
  id: &#39;SOME_ID_OF_YOUR_CHOOSING&#39;,
};

const botsSettings = [{ socketio: socketioSettings }];

const botmaster = new Botmaster({ botsSettings });
botmaster.app.use(express.static(__dirname + &#39;/public&#39;)); //added

botmaster.on(&#39;update&#39;, (bot, update) =&amp;gt; {
  bot.reply(update, &#39;Right back at you&#39;);
});

botmaster.on(&#39;error&#39;, (bot, err) =&amp;gt; {
  console.log(err);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also added the botmaster &amp;lsquo;error&amp;rsquo; event listener, because that&amp;rsquo;s just always good to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;client-side&#34;&gt;Client side&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the Server side, we will create a folder named &amp;lsquo;public&amp;rsquo; within our poject dir. In it, we will have the following three files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;index.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;style.css&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;client_app.js&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that your final tree structure looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;your_project_folder
 app.js
 public
     client_app.js
     index.html
     style.css
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file, we will put some very basic html that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;!doctype html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Botmaster bot&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;link rel=&amp;quot;stylesheet&amp;quot; type=&amp;quot;text/css&amp;quot; href=&amp;quot;style.css&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;chat&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;ul id=&amp;quot;messages&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;form id=&amp;quot;form&amp;quot; action=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;input type=&amp;quot;text&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;text-input&amp;quot; autocomplete=&amp;quot;off&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;lt;button&amp;gt;Send&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/form&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;/socket.io/socket.io.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;client_app.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important line here is the line where we are importing socket.io. This works because socket.io adds a path to our server (in this case, a server created by botmaster under the hood) to serve this exact endpoint.
The other imports are simply the ones we will be creating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt; file, simply add the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;* {
  margin: 0;
  padding: 0;
  box-sizing:
  border-box;
}

body {
  font: 13px Helvetica, Arial;
}

form {
  background: #000;
  padding: 3px;
  position: fixed;
  bottom: 0;
  width: 100%;
}

form input {
  border: 0;
  padding: 10px;
  width: 90%;
  margin-right: .5%;
}

form button {
  width: 9%; background: rgb(130, 224, 255);
  border: none; padding: 10px;
}

#messages {
  list-style-type: none;
  margin: 0;
  padding: 0;
}

#messages li {
  padding: 5px 10px;
}

#messages .botmaster-message {
  background: #eee;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the exact look from the socket.io tutorial mentioned above (and mostly their code too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the &lt;code&gt;client_app.js&lt;/code&gt; file, you should include the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;// the following line could also be: &amp;quot;var socket = io(&#39;ws://&amp;lt;URL&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;PORT_Number&amp;gt;?botmasterUserId=wantedUserId&#39;);&amp;quot;
// if you know you will be communicating with a server different from the one that served you the page you are on
// do something like this: io(&#39;ws://&amp;lt;URL&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;PORT_Number&amp;gt;&#39;);
// this only works because the socket.io library assumes with this syntax that the socket.io server
// lives at the same address as the server that served this page (this should mostly be your case)
var socket = io(&#39;?botmasterUserId=wantedUserId&#39;);

// just get the html elements we will be needing by ID
var form = document.getElementById(&#39;form&#39;);
var textInput = document.getElementById(&#39;text-input&#39;);
var messages = document.getElementById(&#39;messages&#39;);

form.onsubmit = function(event) {
  // just making sure the page isn&#39;t refreshed
  event.preventDefault();
  // don&#39;t do anything if there is no text
  if (!textInput.value) {
    return;
  }
  // Add the user message to the web page
  messages.insertAdjacentHTML(&#39;beforeend&#39;,
    `&amp;lt;li class=&amp;quot;user-message&amp;quot;&amp;gt;${textInput.value}&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;`);
  // create a botmaster compatible message from the text input by user
  const message = {
    text: textInput.value,
  };
  // just send a stringified version of it over the webSocket
  socket.send(JSON.stringify(message));
  // finally, clear the user textInput field
  textInput.value = &#39;&#39;;
};

socket.on(&#39;message&#39;, function(botmasterMessage){
  var messageObject = JSON.parse(botmasterMessage);
  var textMessage = messageObject.message.text;

  messages.insertAdjacentHTML(&#39;beforeend&#39;,
    `&amp;lt;li class=&amp;quot;botmaster-message&amp;quot;&amp;gt;${textMessage}&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;`);
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should have a read through this code to make sure you understand it as that is the code communicating with our botmaster backend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first line, we call: &lt;code&gt;var socket = io(&#39;?botmasterUserId=wantedUserId&#39;);&lt;/code&gt;. This effectively opens up a socket connection with our backend by making a request to something like this: &lt;code&gt;io(&#39;ws://localhost:3000?botmasterUserId=wantedUserId&#39;);&lt;/code&gt;. Here as you can see, we are setting a query param called &lt;strong&gt;botmasterUserId&lt;/strong&gt; to &amp;lsquo;wantedUserId&amp;rsquo;. This is done because we want to make sure that when we are getting updates in our backend, the &lt;code&gt;update.sender.id&lt;/code&gt; part will be what we set it to here and not anything else (by default the randomly allocated socket.id value). This is even more important when your users can connect from different clients and you want to make sure the botmaster reply is propagated to all the clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;form.onsubmit&lt;/code&gt; part, we make sure that the text contained in the input cell is correctly formatted then sent to botmaster via the websocket. We also make sure to display it in our page and to then clear the input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;socket.on(&#39;message&#39;)&lt;/code&gt; part, we simply display the received message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that our code is here, simply go to your command line and run &lt;code&gt;node app.js&lt;/code&gt;. If you now open a browser to 127.0.0.1:3000 you should be able to chat with your pretty useless (for now) bot. Just like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jdwuarin.github.io/botmaster/images/socket.io_setup_1.png?width=90%&#34; alt=&#34;Socket.io Setup 1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;security&#34;&gt;Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering how you can secure your Botmaster socket.io app. I.e. how can you make sure that a client connecting with a certain id really is who they claim they are. Well, this part is actually left to you, the developer to do. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to make any assumptions with regards to what people would want to use to secure their app. So what I do is expose the &lt;code&gt;socket.io&lt;/code&gt; server object through the bot object. It can be accessed in the following way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;socketioBot.ioServer
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to register a middleware function to your socker.io server as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-js&#34;&gt;socketioBot.ioServer.use((socket, next) =&amp;gt; {
  if (socket.request.headers.cookie) return next();
  next(new Error(&#39;Authentication error&#39;));
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is shamelessly stolen from the socket.io documentation here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://socket.io/docs/server-api/#namespace#use(fn:function):namespace&#34;&gt;http://socket.io/docs/server-api/#namespace#use(fn:function):namespace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This function will be executed every time there is an incoming socket connection. Indeed, no need to do so on every message as once the connection is made, all transfers are secured on the open socket. That&amp;rsquo;s really the whole point of webSockets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>